Finding Aid for Office of Academic Planning and Analysis (University of Michigan) records, 1970-2002 (bulk 1970-1982)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of Academic Planning and Analysis (University of Michigan) records 1970-2002 1970-1982
University of Michigan. Office of Academic Planning and Analysis.
93841 Bimu 2
Unit of the Office of Vice President for Academic Affairs, established in 1974 for purpose of conducting research on academic administration at University of Michigan and coordinating evaluation and planning activities of the VPAA and units under its jurisdiction. Successor of the Office of Institutional Research. Primarily records of the Evaluation and Planning Project, 1974-1979, a study of all academic and academically related units under the Vice President for Academic Affairs. Includes correspondence, grant reports, evaluations of academic units, and planning documents. Also miscellaneous college and school accreditation reports.
14 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor 6735 ) was received from the unit in September 1988. The last accession was in 2002
The record group is open without restriction.
The Office of Academic Planning and Analysis (OAPA) was founded as the Office of Institutional Research in 1962. Dr. Donald Lelong was the Director of the office from 1967 to 1973. Under Lelong's direction, steps were taken to align the activities of the office to support university-wide systematic and comprehensive planning. In 1973, the office was renamed to the Office of Academic Planning and Analysis due to a subsequent administrative reorganization. It was at this time that the office acquired new responsibilities including developing planning structure and procedures, conducting specific evaluation and planning studies, and evaluating and planning data to aid in decision making.1 The office also transferred back to reporting to the Vice-President for Academic Affairs from reporting to the Office of the Vice-President for State Relations and Planning from 1969 to 1973.
Through the 1970s the office continue to evolve from data collection to strategic planning. One such project that moved the office towards strategic planning activities built on the work of the three committees overseen by the Office of Budgets and Planning (Long Term Planning, Program Evaluation, and Budget Priorities). In 1974, the OAPA developed an evaluation and planning project linking evaluation of academic units to planning and budgeting activities within the Office of Academic Affairs. As originally conceived, the project was to be implemented in three phases over a three year period. The ultimate goal of the project was to improve the processes by which the university: a) evaluated its activities and programs, b) established priorities, and c) allocated resources. A series of grants were obtained from the Carnegie Foundation beginning in 1975 to conduct case studies of the planning process at other universities and to formulate procedures for the Evaluation and Planning Project. The project encompassed academic units (colleges, schools, and departments) academically related units, and academic service units. Impetus for the project came in part from the budget crisis the university faced in the mid-1970s.
In Phase I of the project, each unit answered an OAPA questionnaire designed to elicit an articulation of the unit's objectives and their operational implications. Phase II consisted of the evaluation of each unit's operations in light of the objectives stated in Phase I. In Phase III, each unit delineated preferred courses of actions and contingency alternatives based on the results of Phase I and Phase II. This resulted in a "Memorandum of Understanding" between the unit and OAPA intended to serve as operating guidelines for the unit over the next five years. Although originally seen as an ongoing process of periodic review, the Evaluation and Planning Project was significantly altered and eventually abandoned as a distinct project when Harold Shapiro succeeded Frank Rhodes as Vice President for Academic Affairs in 1977.
The office again changed its name in 1997 to the Office of Budget and Planning. The office reports to Associate Vice President for Budget, Planning and Administration within the Office of the Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs. Glenna Schweitzer currently serves as the Director of the office (2002). The office provides online access to the Standard Survey Response Document (SSRD) and University Common Data Set. This information is available at http://www.umich.edu/~oapainfo.
The records of the Office of Academic Planning and Analysis document the activities of the office from 1970 to 1982. This period includes the transition of the office from the Office of Institutional Research to the Office of Academic Planning and Analysis and the concurrent shift of core office activities from data collection to planning and analysis. One such analysis and planning activity that is well documented in the records is the Evaluation and Planning Project, 1974-1982. These records both document the planning process as well as provide a unique portrait of the academic units which reported to the Vice President for Academic Affairs. There is also material relating to formal unit reviews and self-studies, 1978-1982, that were not formally part of the Evaluation and Planning Project. In addition to the records from the 1970-1982 period, the record group includes a complete sequence of the Standard Survey Response Document (SSRD) starting in 1991. The records of the Office of Academic Planning and Analysis are organized into four series: Administrative Files, Unit Reviews, Correspondence, and Standard Survey Response Document.
Subjects:
Universities and colleges--Departments--Evaluation.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Urban Planning.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; University of Michigan. College of Pharmacy.; University of Michigan. Evaluation and Planning Project.; University of Michigan--Law School.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. Office of Academic Planning and Analysis.; University of Michigan--Planning.; University of Michigan. School of Art.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; University of Michigan. School of Information and Library Studies.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; University of Michigan. School of Social Work.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Academic Affairs.
- Administrative Files
  The series Administrative Files, 1972-1982 (8.5 linear feet) documents the planning, implementation, and evaluation of the project. Major sub-series include the Background and Historical Files, Carnegie Foundation Sponsored Studies, Enrollment Studies, Phase I Administration, and Phase II Administration. The Background and Historical Files (four folders) include a partial chronology of the project, documents on the planning process at Michigan and other universities, and the monograph Implementation of Formal Planning: Strategies for the Large University, by Donald C. Lelong and Martha Hinman, which summarizes and evaluates the project. The Carnegie Foundation Sponsored Studies sub-series includes grant proposals, 1975 and 1976; Correspondence, 1975-1978; Reports to Carnegie Foundation, 1976-1980; and materials relating to two of the case studies sponsored by Carnegie. Academic Planning Case Studies, 1976-1978, documents Nick L. Poulton's study of the planning process at five major universities. The study provided essential background and comparative information for the Evaluation and Planning Project.
  - Background and Historical Material
    - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - History, "The History of Institutional Research at the University of Michigan: An Overview," by Ruth E. Kallio, April 22, 1981 (Box 1)
    - "Implementation of Formal Planning," 1982 (Box 1)
      (Project summary and evaluation)
    - Correspondence, General 1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Foundation Sponsored Studies
    - Grant Proposals
      - Sussman 1975 (Box 1)
      - Rhodes 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Reports to Carnegie Foundation
      - 1976-1980, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1975-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Academic Planning Case Studies 1976-1978
      (conducted by Nick L. Poulton)
      - Proposal/Report/Correspondence (Box 1)
      - California-Berkeley (Box 1)
      - Colorado State (Box 1)
      - Illinois (Box 1)
      - Minnesota (Box 1)
      - Stanford (Box 1)
      - Case studies of UM Evaluation and Planning Process, FERA (Formative Evaluation Research Associates), 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Enrollment Studies 1977-1980
    The Enrollment Studies sub-series, 1972-1978, provides information on enrollment patterns and projections for some academic units in the Evaluation and Planning Project. The Phase I Administration and Phase II Administration sub-series of the Administrative Files series include planning documents, questionnaires and evaluation forms, and records on coordination and administration of each phase. The Phase I Administration sub-series is arranged alphabetically by academic unit, academically related unit, or academic service unit. Within the academic unit section, larger schools and colleges (e.g. Business, Engineering, LS&A, and Medicine) are subdivided by department. The file for each academic unit typically includes a "Summary of Objectives and Trends", a "Responses to the Phase I Evaluation and Planning Questionnaire", and a summary of the "Phase I Conference." In addition there may be some correspondence between the unit and OAPA.
    - General
      - Advisory Committee (Box 2)
      - Enrollment and Teaching Staff Targets Project (Box 2)
      - Literature, Science & Arts Enrollment (Box 2)
      - Enrollment Data 1972-1978 (Box 2)
    - Evaluation Systems (Box 2)
    - Information Profiles (Box 2)
      (analysis of categories of information to be collected)
  - Phase I Administration
    - Coordination of Phase I (Box 2)
    - Drafts of Phase I Planning Documents, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Phase I Questionnaires (Box 2)
    - Phase I Evaluations, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Phase I Follow-up, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Phase II Administration
    The Phase II Administration sub-series is arranged in essentially the same manner. The Phase II files for each unit (which also encompass material technically generated as part of Phase III) include a "Memorandum of Understanding" between the unit and OAPA. The memorandum refined the units service and research objectives; outlined staffing priorities, including affirmative action goals; stated agreements reached on projected facilities, equipment, space and funding needs; and outlined areas for cooperation with other units. The file for each unit may also include correspondence and supporting documentation.
    - Phase II Planning Documents, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Coordination of Phase II (Box 2)
    - Phase II Working Documents (Box 2)
    - Program Evaluation Committee 1976 (Box 2)
      (minutes, memos, etc)
    - University Relations Project (Box 2)
    - Architecture and Urban Planning, College of (Box 3)
    - Art, School of (Box 3)
    - Business Administration, School of, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Dentistry, School of, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Education, School of, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Engineering, College of, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Law School (includes Institute for Continuing Legal Education and Law Library) (Box 3)
    - Library School (Box 3)
    - Literature, Science & Arts, College of
      - General, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Programs and Centers, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Museums (Box 4)
      - Laboratories and Field Stations (Box 4)
    - Medical School, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Music, School of, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Natural Resources, School of, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Nursing, School of, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Pharmacy, College of (Box 5)
    - Public Health, School of, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Social Work, School of (Box 5)
    - University Library (Box 5)
    - General
      - Admissions (Box 5)
      - Financial Aid (Box 5)
      - Continuing Education for Women (Box 5)
      - Opportunity Program (Box 5)
      - Orientation (Box 5)
      - Registrar (Box 5)
      - Scheduling Office (Box 5)
    - Academically Related Units
      - General (Questionnaire review) (Box 5)
      - Audio-Visual Education Center (Box 5)
      - Center for Human Growth and Development (Box 5)
      - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (Box 5)
      - Clements Library (Box 5)
      - Extension Service (Box 5)
      - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disorders (Box 6)
      - Institute of Gerontology (Box 6)
      - Institute of Labor & Industrial Relations (Box 6)
      - Michigan Historical Collections (Box 6)
      - Museum of Art (Box 6)
      - Periodic Health Appraisal (Box 6)
      - Professional Theater Program (Box 6)
      - Public Policy Studies (Box 6)
      - Television Center (Box 6)
      - Rackham Graduate School
        - General, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Interdisciplinary Instructional Programs, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Academic Affairs (Box 6)
      - Office of Academic Planning and
        - Correspondence (Box 6)
        - General 1976-1978 (Box 6)
        - Relating to Memoranda of Understanding, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Priority Fund (Box 6)
        - Coordinators Meetings (Box 6)
    - Unit Memoranda of Understanding
      - Architecture and Urban Planning, College of (Box 6)
      - Art, School of (Box 6)
      - Dentistry, School of (Box 6)
      - Education, School of (Box 6)
      - Engineering, College of (Box 7)
      - Library Science, School of (Box 7)
      - Literature, Science and Art, College of (Box 7)
      - Medical School (Box 7)
      - Music, School of (Box 7)
      - Natural Resources, School of (Box 7)
      - Nursing, School of (Box 7)
      - Pharmacy, College of (Box 7)
      - Public Health, School of (Box 7)
      - Social Work School of (Box 7)
    - Academically Related Units
      - General (Box 7)
      - Center for Human Growth and Development (Box 7)
      - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (Box 7)
      - Clements Library (Box 7)
      - Extension Service (Box 7)
      - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disorders (Box 7)
      - Institute of Gerontology (Box 7)
      - Institute of Labor & Industrial Relations (Box 7)
      - Michigan Historical Collections (Box 7)
      - Michigan Media (Television Center) (Box 7)
      - Museum of Art (Box 7)
      - Periodic Health Appraisal (Box 7)
      - Professional Theatre Program (Box 7)
      - Public Policy Studies (Box 7)
      - Rackham Graduate School
        - General (Box 8)
        - Museum Practice (Box 8)
    - Academic Service Units, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Peer Information Exchange
      - Preliminary Comparisons (all schools and colleges) (Box 8)
      - Dentistry (Box 8)
      - Engineering, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Nursing (Box 8)
    - Budget and Planning 1978-1981 (Box 8)
    - Planning Process 1981 (Box 8)
- Unit Reviews
  The Unit Review series, 1978-1983 (3.5 linear feet) includes records that were not part of the Evaluation and Planning Project. Some of these records were generated by OAPA activities while others appear to have been simply forwarded to the office. The series is divided into two sub-series: Formal Reviews conducted by the VPAA and Self-Studies and External Reviews conducted as part of a unit's accreditation process. The Formal Reviews sub-series includes materials on the School of Art, School of Education, Michigan Media, and Department of Recreational Sports. These are not complete files on the review process but may supplement material in the records of the respective units. The School of Art files (7 folders) include reports of the Executive Officers Public Meeting, 14 March 1983, to discuss the review; letters from faculty, alumni, students, and parents protesting proposals to scale back the Art School; and general material on the review. The School of Education files (4 folders) are composed of testimony and statements presented at four public hearings held as part of the review process. The Michigan Media review files (4 folders) consist primarily of memoranda between OAPA and VPAA concerning plans to severely downsize Michigan Media, correspondence, and letters of support for the services offered by Michigan Media. The Recreational Sports review file includes the "Report of the Subcommittee on Recreational Sports," 25 March 1981, and correspondence relating to the review. The Self-Studies and External Reviews sub-series includes: the School of Dentistry, 1979 accreditation report; Law School, 1978 self study and report of the American Association of Law Schools; Library Science, 1982 self-study and 1983 ALA accrediting report; Medical School, 1982 report of the ad-hoc survey team; and School of Nursing, 1979 self-study.
  - Formal Reviews
    - Art, School of 1982-1983
      - General (Box 8)
      - Executive Officers Public Meeting (Box 8)
      - Letters, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Education, School of, 1982
      - Testimony at Public Hearings
        - October 26 (Box 8)
        - October 30 (Box 8)
        - November 1 (Box 9)
        - November 3 (Box 9)
    - Michigan Media 1981, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Natural Resources, School of 1982-1983
      - Index of Review Materials (Box 9)
      - General 1982, 5 folders (Box 9)
      - Review Committee Charge 1982 (Box 9)
      - Review Committee Minutes 1982 (Box 9)
      - Report of the Review Committee 1982 (Box 10)
      - Report Drafts 1982 (Box 10)
      - Post-Report Materials 1982-1983 (Box 10)
      - Background Materials for Subcommittee Reports (Box 10)
      - Publicity 1982-1983 (Box 10)
      - Review Questions
        - List (Box 10)
        - Questions 1-28, not including 16 and 21, 26 folders (Box 10)
      - Review Requests 1 and 2, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Support Letters, 6 folders (Box 10)
      - Letter Excerpts (Box 10)
      - Indices to Letters Received (Box 10)
      - Requests for Comments and Acknowledgment of Support Letters (Box 11)
      - "Advice," Michigan Student Assembly's Course and Instructor Evaluation Guide, Winter 1982 (Box 11)
      - "The Environmental Effects of Forestry Operations in Alberta," 1979 (Box 11)
      - "Proposal for Environmental and Socio-Economic Studies of the Gambia River Basin," 1982 (Box 11)
      - "A Manual for Integrative Field Studies" (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous 1982-1983 (Box 11)
      - Audiocassettes, Public Hearings, 5 tapes (Box 11)
    - Recreational Sports, Review 1981 (Box 11)
  - Self-Studies and External Reviews
    - Dentistry, School of, Evaluation Report of the Commission on Dental Accreditation 1979 (Box 11)
    - Engineering, College of, Accreditation Report 1982 (Box 11)
    - Law School 1978 Self-Study and Report of the American Association of Law Schools (Box 11)
    - Library Science, School of (Box 11)
    - 1982 Self-Study Report, 2 volumes (Box 11)
    - 1983 ALA Accrediting Report (Box 11)
    - Medical School 1982 Report of Ad-Hoc Survey Team (Box 11)
    - Nursing 1979 Self-Study (Box 11)
    - "Report on Student Residency Issues," 1987 (Box 11)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series, 1970-1982 (2.75 linear feet), comprises the chronological incoming and outgoing office communications file. The series includes correspondence both from the Office of Institutional Research and the Office of Academic Planning and Analysis. There may be some overlap between a segment of correspondence in this series and the correspondence contained in the Administrative Files series.
  - 1971-1975, 12 folders (Box 12)
  - 1976-1981, 20 folders (Box 13)
  - 1981-1984, 5 folders (Box 14)
- Standard Survey Response Document 1991-2001
  The Standard Survey Response Document series, 1991-2001 (.25 linear feet and 1 CD-ROM), is largely comprised of the Standard Survey Response Document (SSRD). The Office began producing the SSRD document annually in 1991. The document is a compilation of statistical data answering the most commonly asked about questions that the office receives in surveys and questionnaires.
  Beginning with the 2001-2002, the report is disseminated solely through the office's website. The 2001-2002 web-based document published by the office on the office's website has been captured and is available in this series on CD-ROM. The website contains the 2001-2002 Standard Survey Response Document, Common Data Set for the years 1998-2001, Data Element Definitions for CRAS (College Resources Analysis System), and the 2004 Budget Files organized by academic unit.
  - Release date, 1 optical disks CD-ROMs
    - January 27, 1992 (Box 1)
    - February 1993 (Box 1)
    - March 1994 (Box 1)
    - March 1995 (Box 1)
    - January 1996 (Box 1)
    - February 1997 (Box 1)
    - March 4, 1998 (Box 1)
    - February 12, 1999 (Box 1)
    - February 28, 2000 (Box 1)
    - March 19, 2001 (Box 1)
    - October 18, 2002 (Box 1)